Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...
The Center for Applied Sciences
Last time we began...
Trying to...
We began by trying to navigate our way through...
Kant's Moral Theory
Now, fully to make sense of Kant's moral theory in
the groundwork requires that we be able to answer three questions.
How can duty and autonomy go together?
What's the great dignity in answering to duty?
It would seem that these two ideas are
opposed, duty and autonomy. What's Kant's answer to that?
Need someone here to speak up on
Kant's behalf. Does he have an answer?
Yes, go ahead, stand up.
Kant believes that you only act autonomously when you
are pursuing something only in the name of duty
and not because of your own circumstances.
Such as, like you're only doing something good
and moral if you're doing it because of duty
and not because of something of your own personal gain.
Now why is that acting out, what's your name?
Mine is Matt.
Matt, why is that acting out of
freedom? I hear what you're saying about duty.
Because you choose to accept those moral laws in yourself
and they're not brought on from outside upon onto you.
Okay, good. Because acting out of
duty is following a moral law...
That you impose on yourself.
That you impose on yourself. That's what makes...
Yes.
...duty compatible with freedom.
Yeah.
Okay, that's good, Matt. That is
Kant's answer. That's great, thank you.
So, Kant's answer is, it is not insofar as
I am subject to the law that I have dignity,
but rather insofar as with regard to
that very same law, I'm the author.
And I'm subordinated to that law on that
grounds that I took it, as Matt just said,
I took it upon myself. I willed that law.
So, that's why for Kant, acting according to
duty and acting freely, in the sense of autonomously,
are one and the same.
But that raises the question,
how many moral laws are there?
Because if dignity consists in being governed
by a law that I give myself,
what's to guarantee that my conscience,
my conscience will be the same as your conscience?
Who has Kant's answer to that? Yes.
Because a moral law is
not contingent upon subjective conditions,
it would transcend all
particular differences between people,
and so would be a universal law.
And in this respect, there would only be
one moral law, because it would be supreme.
Right. That's exactly right. What's your name?
Kelly.
So, Kelly, Kant believes
that if we choose freely, out
of our own consciences, the moral law,
we're guaranteed to come up with
one and the same moral law.
Yes.
And that's because when I choose,
it's not me, Michael Sandel, choosing.
It's not you, Kelly, choosing for yourself.
What is it exactly?
Who is doing the choosing?
Who's the subject? Who's the agent who's doing the choosing?
Reason.
Well, reason... Pure reason.
Pure reason. And what you mean
by pure reason is what exactly?
Well, pure reason is, like we were saying before,
not subject to any external conditions
that may be imposed on it.
Good. That's great.
So, the reason that does the
willing, the reason that governs my will,
when I will the moral law,
is the same reason that operates when you choose,
the moral law, for yourself.
Yes.
And that's why it's possible to
act autonomously, to choose for myself,
for each of us to
choose for ourselves, as autonomous beings,
and for all of us to
wind up willing the same moral law,
the categorical imperative.
But then there is one
big and very difficult question left.
Even if you accept,
everything that Matt and Kelly have said so far.
How is a categorical imperative possible?
How is morality possible?
To answer that question, Kant says
we need to make a distinction.
We need to make a distinction between two standpoints.
Two standpoints from which
we can make sense of our experience.
Let me try to explain what
he means by these two standpoints.
As an object of experience,
I belong to the sensible world.
There, my actions are determined
by the laws of nature,
and by the regularities of cause and effect.
But as a subject of experience,
I inhabit an intelligible world,
and here, being independent of the laws of nature,
I am capable of autonomy,
capable of acting according to a law I give myself.
Now Kant says that only from this second standpoint
can I regard myself as free,
for to be independent of determination
by causes in the sensible world
is to be free.
If I were wholly an empirical being,
as the utilitarians assume,
if I were a being wholly and only subject
to the deliverances of my senses,
to pain and pleasure and hunger and thirst and appetite,
if that's all there were to humanity,
we wouldn't be capable of freedom.
Kant reasons.
Because in that case,
every exercise of will
would be conditioned by the desire for some object.
In that case, all choice would be heteronymous choice,
governed by the pursuit of some external end.
When we think of ourselves as free, Kant writes,
we transfer ourselves
into the intelligible world as members
and recognize the autonomy of the will.
That's the idea of the two standpoints.
So, how are categorical imperatives possible?
Only because the idea of freedom
makes me a member of an intelligible world.
Now, Kant admits,
we aren't only rational beings,
we don't only, in a sense,
only inhabit the intelligible world,
the realm of freedom.
If we did,
if we did,
then all of our actions would invariably accord
with the autonomy of the will.
But precisely because we inhabit simultaneously
the two standpoints, the two realms,
the realm of freedom
and the realm of necessity,
precisely because we inhabit both realms,
there is always potentially a gap
between what we do
and what we ought to do,
between is and ought.
Another way of putting this point,
and this is the point
with which Kant concludes the groundwork,
morality is not
not empirical.
Whatever you see in the world,
whatever you discover through science
can't decide moral questions.
Morality stands at a certain distance from the world,
from the empirical world.
And that's why no science could deliver moral truth.
Now, I want to test Kant's moral theory
with the hardest possible case,
a case that he raises,
the case of the murderer at the door.
Kant says that lying is wrong.
We all know that.
We've discussed why.
Lying is at odds with the categorical imperative.
A French philosopher, Benjamin Constant,
wrote an article,
responding to the groundwork,
where he said,
this absolute prohibition on lying is wrong.
It can't be right.
What if a murderer came to your door
looking for your friend who was hiding in your house,
and the murderer asked you, point blank,
is your friend in your house?
Constant says it would be crazy
to say that the moral
thing to do in that case
is to tell the truth.
Constant says the murderer
certainly doesn't deserve the truth.
And Kant wrote a reply.
And Kant stuck by his principle
that lying even to the murderer at the door
is wrong.
And the reason it's wrong, he said,
is once you start taking consequences into account
to carve out exceptions to the categorical imperative,
you've given up the whole moral framework.
You've become a consequentialist,
or maybe a rule utilitarian.
But most of you,
and most of Kant's readers,
think there's something odd
or something plausible about this answer.
I would like to try to defend Kant
on this point.
And then I want to see whether you
think that my defense is plausible.
And I would want to defend him
within the spirit of his own account of morality.
Imagine that someone comes to your door.
You were asked the question by this murderer.
You're hiding your friend.
Is there a way
that you could avoid telling a lie
without selling out your friend?
Does anyone have an idea
of how you might be able to do that?
Yes.
Stand up.
I was just going to say
if I were to let my friend
in my house to hide in the first place,
I'd probably make a plan with them.
So I'd be like,
hey, I'll tell the murderer you're here.
But escape.
And that's one of the options mentioned.
But I'm not sure that's a Kantian option.
You're still lying, though.
No, because he's in the house,
but he won't be.
Oh, I see.
All right, good enough.
One more try.
If you just say you don't know where he is
because he might not be locked in the closet,
he might have left the closet,
you have no clue where he could be.
So you would say, I don't know,
which wouldn't actually be a lie
because you weren't at that very moment
looking in the closet.
Exactly.
So it would be, strictly speaking, true.
Yes.
And yet possibly deceiving.
Misleading.
But still true.
What's your name?
I'm David.
I'm a lawyer.
What's your name?
John.
All right, John has...
Now, John may be on to something.
John, you're really offering us
the option of a clever evasion
that is, strictly speaking, true.
This raises the question
whether there is a moral difference
between an outright lie
and a misleading truth.
From Kant's point of view,
there actually is a world of difference
between a lie and a misleading truth.
Why is that?
Even though both might have the same consequences.
But then remember,
Kant doesn't base morality on consequences.
He bases it on formal adherence to the moral law.
Now, sometimes,
in ordinary life,
we make exceptions
for the general rule against lying
with a white lie.
What is a white lie?
It's a lie to make...
Well, to avoid hurting someone's feelings,
for example.
It's a lie that we think of
as justified by the consequences.
Now, Kant could not endorse a white lie,
but perhaps he could endorse
a misleading truth.
Suppose someone gives you a tie.
It's a gift.
And you open the box,
and it's just awful.
What do you say?
Thank you.
Thank you?
You could say thank you.
But they're waiting to see what you think of it.
Or they ask you,
what do you think of it?
You could tell a white lie and say,
it's beautiful.
But that wouldn't be permissible
from Kant's point of view.
Could you say,
not a white lie, but a misleading truth?
You open the box and you say,
I've never seen a tie like that before.
Thank you.
You shouldn't have.
That's good.
Can you think of a contemporary political leader
who engaged...
You can?
Who are you thinking of?
Remember the whole carefully worded denials
in the Monica Lewinsky affair of Bill Clinton?
Now, those denials actually became
the subject of very explicit debate and argument
during the impeachment hearings.
Take a look at the following
excerpts from Bill Clinton.
Is there something, do you think,
morally at stake in the distinction
between a lie
and a misleading, carefully couched truth?
I want to say one thing to the American people.
I want you to listen to me.
I'm going to say this again.
I did not have sexual relations with that woman,
Ms. Lewinsky.
I never told anybody to lie,
not a single time, never.
These allegations are false.
Did he lie to the American people
when he said, I never had sex with that woman?
You know, he doesn't believe he did,
and because of the...
Let me explain, Congressman.
What he said was to the American people
that he did not have sexual relations.
And I understand you're not going to like this,
Congressman, because you will see it
as a hair-splitting, evasive answer.
But in his own mind, his definition was not...
Okay, I understand that argument.
Okay.
All right.
So there you have the exchange.
Now, at the time, you may have thought
this was just a legalistic, hair-splitting exchange
between a Republican who wanted to impeach Clinton
and a lawyer who was trying to defend him.
But now, in the light of Kant,
do you think there is something morally at stake
in the distinction between a lie
and an evasion,
a true but misleading statement?
I'd like to hear from defenders of Kant,
people who think there is a distinction.
Are you ready to defend Kant?
Well, I think when you try to say that lying
and misleading truths are the same thing,
you're basing it on a consequentialist argument,
which is that they achieve the same thing.
But the fact of the
matter is, you told the truth,
and you intended that people would believe
what you were saying, which was the truth,
which means it is not morally
the same as telling a lie
and intending that they believe it is the truth,
even though it's not true.
Good. What's your name?
Diana.
So Diana says that Kant has a point here.
And it's a point that might even
come to the aid of Bill Clinton.
And that is...
Well, what about that?
Someone over here.
For Kant, motivation is key.
So if you give to someone because primarily
you want to feel good about yourself,
Kant would say that has no moral worth.
Well, with this, the motivation is the same.
It's to sort of mislead someone, it's to lie,
it's to sort of throw them off the track,
and the motivation is the same.
So there should be no difference.
Okay, good.
So here, isn't the motive the same, Diana?
What do you say to this argument that,
well, the motive is the same.
In both cases, there is the attempt,
or at least the hope,
that one's pursuer will be misled.
Well, that...
You could look at it that way,
but I think that the fact is that
your immediate motive is that they should believe you.
The ultimate consequence of that
is that they might be deceived
and not find out what was going on.
But your immediate motive is that they should believe you
because you're telling the truth.
May I help a little?
Sure.
You and Kant.
Why don't you say...
And what's your name? I'm sorry.
Wes.
Why don't you say to Wesley,
it's not exactly the case
that the motive in both cases
is to mislead.
They're hoping, they're hoping that the person
will be misled by the statement,
I don't know where they are,
or I never had sexual relations.
You're hoping that they will be misled,
but in the case where you're telling the truth,
your motive is to mislead while at the same time
telling the truth and honoring the moral law
and staying within the bounds of the categorical imperative.
I think Kant's answer would be...
Diana, yes?
Yes.
You like that?
I do.
Okay.
So my answer would be,
unlike a falsehood, unlike a lie,
a misleading truth pays a certain homage to duty.
And the homage it pays to duty
is what justifies that the work,
even the work of evasion.
Diana, yes?
You like...
Okay.
And so there is something,
some element of respect
for the dignity of the moral law
in the careful evasion,
because Clinton could have told an outright lie,
but he didn't.
And so I think Kant's...
Kant's insight here is,
in the carefully couched but true evasion,
there is a kind of homage
to the dignity of the moral law
that is not present in the outright lie.
And that, Wesley,
is part of the motive.
It's part of the motive.
Yes, I hope he will be misled.
I hope the murderer will run down the road
or go to the mall looking for my friend
instead of the closet.
I hope that will be the effect.
I can't control that.
I can't control the consequences.
But what I can control
is standing by and honoring,
however I pursue,
the ends I hope will unfold.
To do so in a way
that is consistent with respect for the moral law.
Wesley, I don't think, is entirely persuaded.
But at least this brings out,
this discussion brings out,
some of what's at stake,
what's morally at stake
in Kant's notion of the categorical imperative.
As long as any effort is involved
in the moral law,
it's not a matter of
whether the effort is involved.
I would say that the contract is valid
and it should take effect.
But why?
What was, what morally can you point to?
For example, two people agree to be married
and one suddenly calls the other
and in two minutes say,
I changed my mind.
Does the contract have obligation on both sides?
Well, I'm tempted to say no.
Fine.
Thank you.
Thank you,
thank you.
Thank you.
Last time,
we talked about Kant's categorical imperative
and we considered the way he applied
the idea of the categorical imperative
to the case of lying.
I want to turn briefly to one other application
of Kant's moral theory
and that's his political theory.
Now, Kant says,
that just laws arise from
a certain kind of social contract.
But this contract, he tells
us, is of an exceptional nature.
What makes the contract exceptional is
that it's not an actual contract
that happens when people come together and try
to figure out what the Constitution should be.
Kant points out that the contract that generates
justice is what he calls an idea of reason.
It's not an actual contract among actual
men and women gathered in a constitutional convention.
Why not?
I think Kant's reason is that actual men
and women gathered in a real constitutional convention
would have different interests,
values, aims,
and there would also be differences of bargaining power
and differences of knowledge among them.
And so the laws that would result from their deliberations
wouldn't necessarily be just,
wouldn't necessarily conform to principles of right,
but would simply reflect
the differences of bargaining power,
the special interests,
the fact that some might know more than others
about law or about politics.
So Kant says a contract that generates principles of right
is merely an idea of reason,
but it has undoubted practical reality,
because it can oblige every legislator to
frame his laws in such a way
that they could have been produced by
the united will of the whole nation.
So Kant is a contractarian,
but he does not believe that the laws that
he has created, the laws that he has created,
are the laws that he has created. He
believes that the laws that he has created,
are the laws that he has created,
he believes that the laws that he has created,
and he doesn't trace the
origin or the rightness of law
to any actual social contract.
This gives rise to an obvious question.
What is the moral force
of a hypothetical contract,
a contract that never happened?
That's the question we take up today.
But in order to investigate it,
we need to turn to a modern philosophy,
John Rawls,
who worked out in his book,
A Theory of Justice,
in great detail,
an account of a hypothetical agreement
as the basis for justice.
Rawls' theory of justice,
in broad outline,
is parallel to Kant's in two important respects.
Like Kant,
Rawls was a critic of utilitarianism.
Each person possesses an inviolability
founded on justice, Rawls writes,
that even the welfare of
society as a whole cannot override.
The rights secured by justice
are not subject to political bargaining
or to the calculus of social interests.
The second respect
in which Rawls' theory
follows Kant's
is on the idea
that principles of justice,
properly understood,
can be derived from a hypothetical social contract,
not an actual one.
And Rawls works this out
in fascinating detail
with the device
of what he calls the veil of ignorance.
The way to arrive at a rule of law,
is to arrive
at the rights,
the basic rights
that we must respect.
The basic framework of rights and duties
is to imagine
that we were gathered together
trying to choose the principles
to govern our collective lives
without knowing
certain important particular facts
about ourselves.
That's the idea of the veil of ignorance.
Now what would happen if we
gathered together,
just as we are here,
and tried to come up with principles of justice
to govern our collective life?
There would be a cacophony of proposals,
of suggestions,
reflecting people's different interests.
Some are strong, some are weak.
Some are rich, some are poor.
So Rawls says,
imagine instead
that we are gathered
in an original position of equality.
And what assures the equality
is the veil of ignorance.
Imagine that we are all behind
a veil of ignorance
which temporarily
abstracts from, or brackets,
hides from us.
Who in particular we are.
Our race, our class, our place in society,
our strengths, our weaknesses,
whether we're healthy or unhealthy.
Then, and only then,
Rawls says,
the principles we would agree to
would be principles of justice.
That's how the hypothetical contract works.
What is the moral force
of this kind of hypothetical agreement?
Is it stronger or weaker than a real agreement,
an actual social contract?
In order to answer that question,
we have to look hard at the moral force
of actual contracts.
There are really two questions here.
One of them is,
how do actual contracts bind me,
or obligate me?
Question number one.
And question number two,
how do actual, real life contracts
justify the terms that they produce?
If you think about it,
this is in line with Rawls and Kant,
the answer to the second question,
how do actual contracts justify
the terms that they produce,
the answer is they don't.
At least not on their own.
Actual contracts are not
self-sufficient moral instruments.
Of any actual contract or agreement,
it can always be asked,
is it fair what they agreed to?
The fact of the agreement
never guarantees the fairness of the agreement.
And we know this by
looking at our own constitutional convention.
It produced a constitution
that permitted slavery to persist.
It was agreed to,
it was an actual contract,
but that doesn't establish
that the laws agreed to,
all of them, were just.
Well then, what is the moral force
of actual contracts?
To the extent that they bind us,
they obligate in two ways.
Suppose, maybe here it would help
to take an example.
We make an agreement,
a commercial agreement.
I promise to pay you $100
if you will go harvest
and bring to me 100 lobsters.
We make a deal.
You go out and harvest them
and bring them to me.
I eat the lobsters,
serve them to my friends,
and then I don't pay.
And you say,
but you're obligated.
And I say, why?
What do you say?
Well, we had a deal.
And you benefited.
You ate all those lobsters.
Well, that's a pretty strong argument.
It's an argument that depends, though,
on the fact that I benefited
from your labor.
So, contracts sometimes bind us
insofar as they are instruments
of mutual benefit.
I ate the lobsters.
I owe you the $100
for having gathered them.
But suppose,
now take a second case,
we make this deal.
I'll pay you $100
for 100 lobsters.
And two minutes later,
before you've gone to any work,
I call you back and say,
I've changed my mind.
Now,
there's no benefit.
There's no work on your part.
So there's no element
of reciprocal exchange.
What about in that case?
Do I still owe you?
Merely in virtue of the fact
that we had an agreement?
Who says,
those of you who say yes,
I still owe you?
Why?
Okay, stand up.
Why do I owe you?
I call you back.
After two minutes,
you haven't done any work.
I think I spent the time
and effort in drafting
this contract with you.
And also, I have emotional expectation
that I'll go through the work.
So you took time
to draft the contract,
but we did it very quickly.
We just chatted on the phone.
That wouldn't be a formal form
of contract, though.
Well, I faxed it to you.
It only took a minute.
As long as any effort is involved,
I would say that the contract
is valid and it should take effect.
But why?
What was, what morally
can you point to
that obligates me?
I admit that I agreed.
But you didn't go to any work.
I didn't enjoy any benefit.
Because we might mentally
go through all the work
of harvesting the lobsters.
You mentally went through
the work of harvesting the lobsters.
That's nothing, is it?
It's not much.
Is it worth $100
that you were imagining yourself
going and collecting that?
It may not worth $100,
but it may worth something
to some people.
All right, I'll give you
a buck for it, for that.
But what I, so you're still pointing,
what's interesting,
you're still pointing to
the reciprocal dimension of contracts.
You did or imagined that you did
or looked forward to doing something
on my behalf.
For example, two people agree
to be married,
and one suddenly calls the other
and in two minutes say,
I changed my mind.
Does the contract have obligation
on both sides?
Nobody has paid any work
or nobody has benefited yet.
So, I'm not sure
if I've benefited yet.
Well, I'm tempted to say no.
Fine.
All right.
What's your name?
Julian.
Thank you, Julian.
All right.
That was good.
Now, is there anyone who has,
who agrees with Julian
that I still owe the money?
For any other reason now,
I have, go ahead.
Stand up.
I think if you back out,
it sort of cheapens
the institution of contracts.
Good, but why?
Why does it?
Well, I think this is kind of Kantian,
but there's, you know, almost,
there's a certain intrinsic value
in being able to make contracts
and having, you know,
knowing that people will expect
that you'll go through with that.
Good.
There is some,
it would cheapen the whole idea
of contracts,
which has to do with taking in,
obligation on myself.
Is that, is that the idea?
Yeah, I think so.
What's your name?
Adam.
So Adam points instead,
not to any reciprocal benefit
or mutual exchange,
but to the mere fact
of the agreement itself.
We see here there are really
two different ways in which
actual contracts generate obligations.
One has to do with the act of obligation
of consent as a voluntary act.
And it points,
Adam said this was a Kantian idea,
and I think he's right,
because it points to the ideal of autonomy.
When I make a contract,
the obligation is one that is self-imposed.
And that carries a certain moral weight,
independent of other considerations.
And then there's a second element
of the moral force of contract arguments.
Which has to do with the sense in which
actual contracts are instruments
of mutual benefit.
And this points toward the ideal
of reciprocity.
That obligation can arise,
I can have an obligation to you,
insofar as you do something for me.
Now, we're investigating
the moral force and also the moral limits.
Of actual contracts.
And here I would like to advance an argument
about the moral limits of actual contracts.
Now that we know what moral ingredients
do the work when people come together
and say, I will do this if you do that.
I would like to argue first
that the fact that two people agree
to some exchange,
does not mean that the terms
of their agreement are fair.
When my two sons were young,
they collected baseball cards
and traded them.
And one was, there was a two year age,
there is a two year age difference between them.
And so I had to institute a rule
about the trades,
that no trades are fair
and no trades are complete
until I had approved it.
And the reason is obvious.
The older one knew more about the value
of these cards and so would take advantage
of the younger one.
So that's why I had to review it
to make sure that the agreement,
that the agreements were fair.
Now you may say, well this is paternalism.
Of course it was.
That's what paternalism is for.
That kind of thing.
So what does this show?
What does the baseball card example show?
The fact of an agreement
is not sufficient to establish
the fairness of the terms.
I read some years ago of a case in Chicago.
There was an elderly widow,
an 84 year old widow,
named Rose,
who had a problem in her apartment
with a leaky toilet.
And she signed a contract
with an unscrupulous contractor
who offered to repair her leaky toilet
in exchange for $50,000.
But she had agreed.
She was of sound mind,
maybe terribly naive and unfamiliar
with the price of plumbing.
She had made this agreement.
Luckily, it was discovered.
She went to the bank
and asked to withdraw $25,000.
And the teller said,
what do you need all of that money for?
And she said, well I have a leaky toilet.
And the teller called authorities
and they discovered this unscrupulous contractor.
Now, I suspect that even the most ardent
contractarians in the room,
will agree that the fact
of this woman's agreement
is not a sufficient condition
of the agreement being fair.
Is there anyone who will dispute that?
No one.
Am I missing anyone?
Alex, where are you?
Where are you?
So, maybe there's no dispute then
to my first claim
that an actual agreement
is not necessary to their,
is not a sufficient condition
of their being an obligation.
I want to now make a stronger,
maybe more controversial claim
about the moral limits of actual contracts
that a contractual agreement
has to offer.
A contract or an act of consent
is not only not sufficient,
but it's not even a necessary condition
of their being an obligation.
And the idea here is
that if there is reciprocity,
if there is an exchange,
then a receipt of benefits,
there can be an obligation
even without an act of consent.
One great example of this,
involves the 18th century philosopher,
the Scottish moral philosopher,
David Hume.
When he was young,
Hume wrote a book arguing against Locke's idea
of an original social contract.
Hume heaps scorn on this contractarian idea.
He said it was a philosophical fiction,
one of the most mysterious
and incomprehensible operations
that can possibly be
imagined,
this idea of the social contract.
Many years later,
when he was 62 years old,
Hume had an experience
that put to the test
his rejection of consent
as the basis of obligation.
Hume had a house in Edinburgh.
He rented it to his friend,
James Boswell,
who in turn sublet it to a subtenant.
The subtenant decided
that the house needed some repairs
and a paint job.
He hired a contractor
to do the work.
The painter did the work
and sent the bill to Hume.
Hume refused to pay
on the grounds that he hadn't consented.
He hadn't hired the painter.
The case went to court.
The contractor said,
it's true,
Hume didn't agree,
but the house needed a painting
and I gave it a very good one.
Hume thought this was a bad argument.
The only argument this painter makes
is that the work was necessary
to be done,
but this is no good answer
because by the same rule,
this painter may go through
every house in Edinburgh
and do what he thinks proper to be done
without the landlord's consent
and give the same reason,
that the work was necessary
and that the house was the better for it.
So Hume didn't like the theory
that there could be obligation
to repay a benefit without consent,
but the defense failed,
and he had to pay.
Let me give you one other example
of the distinction
between the consent-based aspect
of obligations
and the benefit-based aspect
and how they sometimes run together.
This is based on a personal experience.
Some years ago,
I was driving across the country
with some friends,
and we found ourselves
in the middle of nowhere
in Hammond, Indiana.
We stopped at a restaurant
and got out of the car,
and when we came back,
our car wouldn't start.
None of us knew much about cars.
We didn't really know what to do
until we noticed that
in the parking lot driving up next to us
was a van,
and on the side it said,
Sam's Mobile Repair Van.
And out of the van came a man,
presumably Sam,
and he came up to us
and he said,
Can I help you?
Here's how I work.
I work by the hour for $50 an hour.
If I fix your car in five minutes,
you owe me the $50,
and if I work on your car for an hour
and can't fix it,
you'll still owe me the $50.
So I said,
Well, what is the likelihood
that you'll be able to fix the car in?
He didn't answer,
but he did start looking under the,
poking around under the steering column.
Short time passed.
He emerged from under the steering column and said,
There's nothing wrong with the ignition system,
but you still have 45 minutes left.
Should I look under the hood?
I said,
Wait a minute.
I haven't hired you.
We haven't made any agreement.
And then he became very angry,
and he said,
Do you mean to say that
if I had fixed your car
while I was working under the steering column
that you wouldn't have paid me?
And I said,
That's a different question.
I didn't go into the distinction
between consent-based and benefit-based obligations.
But I think he had the intuition
that if he had fixed
it while he was poking around,
that I would have owed him the $50,
I shared that intuition.
I would have.
But he inferred from that,
this was the fallacy and the reasoning
that I think lay behind his anger,
he inferred from that fact that therefore,
implicitly,
we had an agreement.
But that, it seems to me, is a mistake.
It's a mistake that fails to recognize the distinction
between these two different aspects of contract arguments.
Yes, I agree, I would have owed him $50
if he had repaired my car during that time.
Not because we had made any agreement,
we hadn't.
But simply because if he had fixed my car,
he would have conferred on me a benefit
for which I would have owed him
in the name of reciprocity and fairness.
So, here's another example
of the distinction between these
two different kinds of arguments,
these two different aspects
of the morality of contract.
Now, I want to hear how many think
I was in the right in that case.
That's reassuring.
Is there anyone who thinks I was in the wrong?
Anyone?
You do?
Why? Go ahead.
Isn't the problem with this is that
any benefit is inherently subjectively defined?
I mean, what if you wanted your car broken
and he had fixed it?
I mean...
No, I didn't want it broken.
Yeah, in this case.
But who would? Who would?
I don't know, someone.
I mean, what if Hume, you know,
what if the painter had painted his house blue
but he hated the color blue?
I mean, you have to sort of define
what your benefit is before the person does it.
Well, all right.
So, what would you conclude from that, though,
for the larger issue here?
Would you conclude that, therefore, consent
is a necessary condition of there being an obligation?
Absolutely.
You would. What's your name?
Nate.
Because otherwise, how can we know, Nate says,
whether there has been an exchange
of equivalent or fair benefits?
Unless we have the subjective valuation,
which may vary one person to the next
of the situation.
All right, that's a fair challenge.
Let me put to you one other example
in order to test the relation between these two aspects
of the morality of contract.
Suppose I get married.
And suppose I discover
that after 20 years of faithfulness on my part,
every year on our trip across the country,
my wife has been seeing another man.
A man with a van on the Indiana toll road.
This part is completely made up, by the way.
Wouldn't I have two different reasons for moral outrage?
One reason could be, we had an agreement.
She broke her promise, referring
to the fact of her consent.
But I would also have
a second ground for moral outrage,
having nothing to do with the contract as such.
But I've been so faithful for my part.
Surely I deserve better than this.
Is this what I'm due in return?
And so on.
So that would point to the element of reciprocity.
Each reason has an independent moral force.
That's the general point.
And you can see this
if you imagine a slight variation
on the marriage case.
Suppose we hadn't been married for 20 years.
Suppose we were just married,
and that the betrayal looked like a lie.
And that it occurred on the way to our honeymoon
in Hammond, Indiana.
After the contract has been made,
but before there is any
history of performance on my part.
Performance of the contract, I mean.
I would still...
Oh, come on, come on.
I would still, with Judy,
I would be able to say,
but you promised.
You promised.
That would isolate the pure element of consent, right?
Where there were no benefit.
Never mind.
You get the idea.
Here's the main idea.
Actual contracts
have their moral force in virtue,
of two distinguishable ideals.
Autonomy and reciprocity.
But in real life,
every actual contract
may fall short,
may fail to realize
the ideals that give contracts their moral force
in the first place.
The ideal of autonomy may not be realized
because there may be a difference in the bargaining.
There may be a difference in the bargaining power
of the parties.
The ideal of reciprocity may not be realized
because there may be a difference of knowledge
between the parties.
And so they may misidentify
what really counts as having equivalent value.
Now,
suppose you were to imagine
a contract
where the ideals of autonomy
and of reciprocity
were not subject to contingency,
but were guaranteed to be realized.
What kind of contract would that have to be?
Imagine a contract among
parties who were equal in power and knowledge
rather than unequal,
who were identically situated
rather than differently situated.
That is the idea
behind Rawls's claim
that the way to think about justice
is from the standpoint of a hypothetical contract
behind a veil of ignorance
that creates a condition of equality
by ruling out
or enabling us to forget for the moment
the differences in power and knowledge
that could, even in principle,
lead to unfair results.
This is why
for Kant and for Rawls,
a hypothetical contract among equals
is the only way
to think about principles of justice.
What will those principles be?
That's the question we'll turn to next time.
Don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of Justice.
Join the conversation.
Take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed
and learn a lot more.
Visit justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.
We'll see you next time.
© transcript Emily Beynon